Guide to the Society of Physiological Neurology Papers
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Society of Physiological Neurology Papers
1937-1943
Ms Coll 39
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.5
(1 box)
The Society of Physiological Neurology was was founded in 1937 as an outgrowth of the American Neurological Association. It held annual meetings from 1938 to 1942. The collection appears to be the archives of the Society and contains correspondence with members and others by the successive chairmen of the annual meeting committees; membership lists; drafts of programs; and attendance records.
Society of Physiological Neurology
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Possibly archived at Yale through Margaret A. Kennard, an active member.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The Society of Physiological Neurology was organized in 1937 by a group of individuals who felt that the American Neurological Association was too oriented to practicing clinicians. Run by an annual committee, the Society was small and highly selective in its membership. It held meetings the day before and in the same location as the ANA from 1938 through 1942. In 1943, the war prevented organizing a meeting. The Society does not appear to have been re-established under this name after the war.
Scope and Contents
The collection appears to be the archives of the Society and contains correspondence with members and others by the successive chairmen of the annual committees, Frederick A. Gibbs, Margaret A. Kennard, Charles D. Aring, Clinton A. Woolsey, and Howard J. Curtis; membership lists; drafts of programs; and attendence records. Abstracts of presentations are included for 1942.
Arrangement
Arranged by year.
Neurology -- Research -- United States; Neurophysiology; Societies, Medical; Aring, Charles D., 1904-; Curtis, Howard J. (Howard James), 1906-; Gibbs, Frederic Andrews, 1903-; Kennard, Margaret Alice, 1899-; Woolsey, Clinton N.; American Neurological Association
- Selection of initial members: Correspondence of Frederick A. Gibbs, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1938 meeting: Correspondence of Frederick A. Gibbs, 1938 March-May (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  The meeting was held May 1, 1838 in Atlantic City, New Jersey.
- 1939 meeting: Correspondence of Margaret A. Kennard, 1939 February-June (Box 1, Folder 3)
  The meeting was held on June 4, 1939 in Atlantic City, New Jersey.
- 1940 meeting: Correspondence of Charles D. Aring, 1940 February-March (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1940 meeting: Correspondence of Charles D. Aring, 1940 April-June (Box 1, Folder 5)
  The meeting was held on June 5, 1940 in Rye, New York.
- 1941 meeting: Correspondence of Clinton N. Woolsey, 1940 June-1941 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
  With membership lists, 1941.
- 1941 meeting: Ballot and questionnaire sent to members, 1941 April-May (Box 1, Folder 7)
  In late April 1941, Clinton N. Woolsey sent a ballot and questionnaire to each member to vote for new members and to indicate their plans for the next meeting.This folder contains the returned ballots and related correspondence.
- 1941 meeting: Correspondence of Clinton N. Woolsey, 1941 May -June (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Correspondence with newly selected members and correspondence concerning the annual meeting. The meeting was held on June 8, 1941 in Atlantic City, New Jersey.
- 1942 meeting: Correspondence of Howard J. Curtis, 1942 March-June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  The meeting was held on June 3, 1942 in Chicago. Folder also contains returns of a postcard ballot regarding the meeting and abstracts of papers presented.
- 1943 memorandum suspending the annual meeting, 1943 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Letter from Howard A Curtis to members. Also an undated note referring to putting papers back in "the archives."